Just before we go on to some of the more advanced metrics, I want to mention for a second something
더 고급 지표로 넘어가기 전에 친칠라 스케일링 법칙을
called the Chinchilla Scaling Law, which is a wonderfully named law coined by the Google DeepMind team
언급하고 싶습니다 구글 딥마인드 팀이 만든 멋진 이름의 법이죠 친칠라
after one of their models called Chinchilla.
모델 이름을 따서요
And it's related to how you think about the number of parameters that you need in a model, the number
모델에서 필요한 매개 변수의 개수와 신경망의 무게에
of weights in the neural network, and what the law says is that the number of parameters, how many
관한 거죠 법에 따르면 매개 변수의 개수는
parameters you have, is roughly proportional to the size of your training data to the number of training
훈련 데이터와 훈련 토큰의 개수에 비례해요
And what that means, basically, is that supposing you've got a model, let's say it's an 8 billion
그 말은 모델이 있다고 가정해 봅시다. 예를 들어 80억 개의 매개 변수 모델이 있다고 합시다.
parameter model, and you get to the point where you start to see that you're getting diminishing returns.
그리고 어느 지점에 도달하면 반환률이 감소하기 시작할 거예요.
Adding in more training data isn't significantly affecting the model.
훈련 데이터를 추가한다고 모델에 큰 영향을 주진 않아요
So you have this sense, okay, I've got now the right amount of training data for this size of model.
그래서 여러분은 이 크기의 모델에 대한 트레이닝 데이터가 적당하다고 느끼죠
This is a good a good match up.
좋은 대결이 될 거예요
We've we've used our training data successfully for the model to learn to its to its most capacity of
훈련 데이터를 성공적으로 활용해 이 모델을 최대한의 학습 능력으로 끌어올렸죠
And the question might be all right.
괜찮은 질문일 수도 있어요
So if I wanted to add more parameters, give the model more flexibility to learn more and to be more,
매개 변수를 더 추가하고 싶다면 모델에 더 유연하게 학습할 수 있고 더 강력하고 미묘한
more powerful and nuanced.
차이를 줄 수 있죠
How many more parameters do I need given extra training data?
훈련용 데이터가 얼마나 더 필요하죠?
And the answer is, if you were then to double the amount of training data from that that point of diminishing
답은 이겁니다. 훈련 데이터를 두 배로 늘린다면 그 시점에서 수익이
returns, you would need double the number of weights you'd need to go from 8 billion to 16 billion
감소할 테고 무게는 두 배가 될 겁니다. 80억에서 160억 매개 변수가
parameters to be able to consume twice the training data and learn from it in an effective way, and
필요할 거예요. 훈련 데이터를 두 배로 쓰고 효과적으로 학습하려면요. 결과적으로 더 강력하고
be that much more powerful and nuanced at the end of it.
미묘하게 표현되려면요.
So it gives you a sense of how many more parameters do you need to absorb more training data effectively.
훈련 데이터를 효과적으로 흡수하려면 매개 변수가 얼마나 더 필요한지 알 수 있죠
And it also gives you the sort of the flip side, the opposite, uh, relationship to that.
그리고 그 이면에는 정반대의 관계도 있어요
If you're if you've been working with a model which is an 8 billion model, and then someone says,
여러분이 80억 모델로 작업했는데 누군가 160억 매개 변수 모델로
we'd like to upgrade to a 16 billion parameter model, let's use that instead.
업그레이드하고 싶다고 하면 그걸 대신 사용하세요
Uh, and you're thinking, all right, well, obviously, if I'm going to take advantage of all of this
이렇게 생각할 수 있죠 이런 추가적인 유연성과
extra flexibility, all of this extra predictive power in this bigger model with more, more dials,
예측력을 이용하려면 더 큰 모델에 다이얼과 추를 더 많이 적용해야 한다고요
How much more training data am I going to need to be able to to take advantage of that?
이를 이용하기 위해 얼마나 더 많은 훈련 데이터가 필요할까요?
And the answer is you would you would roughly need to double the size of your training data set.
그 대답은 훈련 데이터 집합의 두 배가 필요하단 거죠
So that relationship between the number of training tokens and parameters, uh, was, was suggested,
훈련 토큰과 매개 변수의 관계는 몇 년 전에 제안된 것으로
uh, a few years ago, and it stood the test of time.
지금까지도 유효하죠
It turns out that that for transformers for the transformer architecture, this scaling law appears
변압기 구조에서 변압기 규격 법칙이 적용되는 것으로 밝혀졌죠
Well.
글쎄요
And it's a great rule of thumb to keep to hand.
상황에 따라 행동하는 게 경험에서 나온 법칙이죠
All right.
좋아요
With that, let's just move on now to benchmarks.
이제 벤치마크로 넘어가죠
So benchmarks are the common metrics that people talk about uh, which are used to weigh up different
벤치마크는 사람들이 흔히 말하는 측정 기준입니다 다양한 모델을 재는 데 사용되죠
They are a series of tests that are applied and used in various leaderboards, which is where you rank
일련의 테스트가 적용되고 다양한 leaderboard에서 사용됩니다 다양한 LMS의
different, different LMS, uh, to see the different pros and cons of different models.
순위를 매기는 곳이죠 다양한 모델의 장단점을 보는 거예요
Now I've got this table of different benchmarks.
이제 다양한 벤치마크 테이블이 있어요
I'm going to go through them one at a time and get a sense for each one.
하나씩 살펴보면서 감을 잡을 거예요 get it get it
Now, you don't need to remember what each of these benchmarks are because you can always look it up.
이런 벤치마크가 뭔지 기억할 필요는 없어요 언제든 찾아보면 되니까요
It's useful for you to have a sense of it so that it comes back to you quickly.
그런 걸 느끼는 게 도움이 돼요 빨리 돌아오니까요
So definitely focus and take this in and and and do some research.
그러니 집중해서 잘 보고 조사도 좀 하세요
If you have questions.
궁금한 게 있으면요
We're going to see these numbers in some of the analysis that we'll be doing later as we compare different
이 숫자들은 나중에 다른 모델을 비교할 때 분석할 때 볼
models.
거예요
So the first one I'm going to mention of the the seven most common benchmarks you see all over the place.
첫 번째로 말씀드릴 것은 가장 흔한 벤치마크 7가지입니다 어디서나 볼 수 있죠
The first one is called Arc, which is a benchmark that measures scientific reasoning.
첫 번째는 Arc입니다 과학적 추론을 측정하는 척도죠
It's basically a bunch of multiple choice questions.
객관식 문제인 셈이죠
Drop is a language comprehension test which involves looking at text, distilling it, and then doing
Drop은 언어 이해력 테스트로 텍스트를 보고 정제한 다음 텍스트를 추가하거나
things like adding or sorting or counting from that text.
정렬하거나 세는 작업을 하죠
Hella swag, which stands for harder encodings, long context and low shot activities, is a kind of
더 어려운 암호화, 긴 컨텍스트 저가 활동의 약자인 헬 스웨그는 상식적
common sense reasoning test.
추론 테스트의 일종이에요
MLU is super famous.
MLU는 엄청 유명해요
You'll see it all over the place.
어디서나 볼 수 있어요
It was a really common metric that involves reasoning across 57 subjects.
57개 피험자를 추론하는 아주 흔한 측정법이었어요
There's been some there were some questions raised about how well formed the questions were.
질문이 얼마나 잘 구성됐는지에 대해 의문이 제기되기도 했어요
And there's some, some doubts on the effectiveness of them.
효과적인지 의심하는 사람들도 있어요
Lou, it was perhaps overused.
루, 너무 많이 쓴 것 같아요
And you'll see later that there's a variation on Lou which is now more popular called MLU Pro.
나중에 루의 변형 버전이 나오는데 지금은 MLU Pro라고 불리죠
So this has somewhat been replaced.
이건 대체된 거예요
Now, truthful QA is about accuracy and robustness, particularly in adversarial conditions when the
진실한 QA는 정확성과 견고성을 요구합니다 특히 적대적인 상황에서 진실을 말하지 말라고
model is encouraged to not be truthful.
부추기는 모델에서는요
Winogrand is testing that a model can resolve ambiguity in more confusing contexts, and then GSM eight
위노그랜드는 모델이 더 혼란스러운 상황에서 모호함을 해결할 수 있다는 걸 시험합니다 GSM
K grade school math at the eight K level is both math and also word problems that are in elementary
8K 수준의 초등학교 수학은 수학이자 초등학교와 중학교의 단어 문제이기도
and middle school level.
하죠
So these are seven common benchmarks you come across these a lot.
이게 자주 보이는 7가지 공통 벤치마크예요
Uh, keep note of them.
잘 기억해 두세요
They're in the resources.
자원부에 있어요
And you will as I say, these are these are things you will see a lot.
앞으로 이런 걸 많이 보게 될 거예요
And hopefully you will now recognize them.
이제 알아보실 수 있을 거예요